[Today's episode is a double-feature showcasing the "Kabukicho Snow Festival" and "Fireworks In Winter"!!]
[We also have a new ending song, so stay tuned!]
Huh? What happened? The sky is all white.
《新八:あれ… なんだ？ これ…｡
空が 真っ白だ…》
Huh? I'm the one all white...
《あれ？ 真っ白なのは
ﾎﾞｸじゃないか…？》
Huh? Why am I sleeping in a place like this?
《あれ？ なんで ﾎﾞｸ➡
こんなところで 寝てるんだっけ？
あれ？ こんなん
前にもなかったっけ？ あれ…》
Huh? Has something like this happened before? Huh?
["Only Children Play in the Snow"]
(お登勢)今年の冬は
異常気象だか なんだか➡
I'm not sure if there's an abnormal climate system this winter or what, but...
知らないがねぇ…｡
When it's raining, you wash yourself in an outdoor tub!
(お登勢)雨が降れば 行水！
槍が降れば ﾊﾞﾝﾌﾞｰﾀﾞﾝｽ！
If it's raining spears, you'd do a bamboo dance!
どんなときも
楽しむ余裕を 忘れないのが➡
We, as Edoites, believe that whatever happens, we might as well enjoy it!
江戸っ子の心意気ってもんだい！
つ～ことで！
So...
The First Chiki Chiki Kabukicho Snow Festival will commence!
第１回ﾁｷﾁｷかぶき町雪祭り
開催決定！
銀さ～ん！
Gin-san!
I brought some snow.
雪 持ってきました！
(銀時)おう そこ置いとけ｡
Oh, leave it there.
いやぁ… みんな
すごいの作ってますね｡
Wow, everyone is making great sculptures.
いかがわしい雪像ばっか…｡
They're all pretty risque snow statues, though. Well, that's Kabukicho, for you.
まぁ かぶき町らしいっちゃ
らしいけど…｡
ﾎﾞｸら 万事屋は 何を…｡
We, of the Odd Jobs, are...
まぁ こんなとこか…｡
Well, this looks good... And I'll put the column in the middle...
あとは 真ん中に棒を立てて…｡
放送 打ち切られるぅ～！
Our show will be taken off the air!
(銀時)おいおい…
なにすんだ お前は！
Hey, hey, what are you doing?
ｵﾚが その左の玉 作るのに➡
Don't you know how hard I worked to make that ball on the left?!
どれだけ苦労したか
わかってんのか ｺﾗ！
ｱﾝﾀこそ そんなことしたら➡
What about you?!
Don't you know how pissed off the producer will be if you do something like that?!
ﾌﾟﾛﾃﾞｭｰｻｰが どれだけ苦労するか
わかってんですか ｺﾗｧｱ！
Gin-chan, I made the column.
(神楽)銀ちゃん 棒 できたよ｡
ｷｬｱｧｱ～ｯ！ なに持ってんの
神楽ちゃん!!
Whoa! What are you holding, Kagura-chan?!
新八よぉ… お前 なに？
What, Shinpachi?!
I don't know what you think this is, but...
何を勘違いしているか
知らないけどよぉ➡
これ あれだよ…➡
This is the Neo Armstrong Cyclone Jet Armstrong Cannon.
ﾈｵｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ･ｻｲｸﾛﾝｼﾞｪｯﾄ･ｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ砲
だよ｡
ｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ ２回 言ったよ！
You said Armstrong twice! There's no way such an obscene cannon exists!
あるわけねえだろ
こんな卑猥な大砲！
You're in early adolescence and you always have dirty thoughts.
ったく… 思春期は
ｴﾛいことばっか 考えてるから…｡
棒とか 玉があれば
すぐにそっちに話 もってくな！
So whenever you see a pole and couple of balls, you immediately imagine something nasty.
ﾏｼﾞ ｷﾓいｱﾙ
しばらく 私に話しかけないで｡
You're really disgusting. Don't talk to me for a while.
じゃあ いったい何よ それ…｡
Then, what is it, huh?
(長谷川)おいおい なに？
ｵﾒｴらも 来てたの？
Oh, you guys are here, too?
Oh, Hasegawa-san.
あっ 長谷川さん！
Please stop them. Those two are making something really...
ちょっと 止めてくださいよ！
２人が とんでもない物を…｡
なんだよ おい…➡
Hey, isn't that a Neo Armstrong Cyclone Jet Armstrong Cannon?
ﾈｵｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ･ｻｲｸﾛﾝｼﾞｪｯﾄ･ｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ砲
じゃねえか｡
完成度 高えな おい！
It's got a very high-quality finish.
えぇえ～っ!? なんで知ってんの！
What?! How do you know?! Does it really exist? Seriously?
あんの？ ﾏｼﾞで あんの？
ﾎﾞｸだけ 知らないの!?
Am I the only one who doesn't know anything about it?!
江戸城の天守閣を吹き飛ばし➡
It was the Dog Star clan's ultimate weapon.
江戸を開国させちまった
ｲﾇｲ賊の 決戦兵器だ｡
They used it to blow up Edo Castle Tower and force Japan to open up the country.
なに？ こんな かっこ悪い大砲に
やられたんですか ﾎﾞｸらの国は！
What? Our country was beaten with this ugly cannon?
それより ｱﾝﾀ… なんで
こんなとこに いるんだよ？
Anyway, what are you doing here?
Well, I've created my own sculpture for the contest.
いや ｵﾚも個人参加すんだよ｡
なんか ｸﾞﾗﾝﾌﾟﾘ取ったら
賞金 出るらしいじゃん｡
I heard the winner gets a big cash prize.
うぉおぉ～っ！
Wow!
What's this?!
なんすか これ！
I'm not sure what it is, but it looks great!
なんか わかんないけど
すごいじゃないですかぁ！
いやいや… そんな
たいしたもんじゃねえよ｡
Well, it's nothing really.
I tend to get immersed in anything I do, so I couldn't stop... I call it "Flight."
ｵﾚ 結構 凝り性だからさぁ
止まらなくなっちゃって…｡
ﾀｲﾄﾙは 『飛翔』…｡
It's fantastic! Are you the model for this, Hasegawa-san?
いやぁ… すごいですよ これ！
長谷川さんが ﾓﾃﾞﾙなんですか？
(長谷川)えっ？ まぁ…➡
Huh? Well, I put a lot of my heart and soul into it, so it ended up looking like me.
愛情 入れすぎて
似てしまったというか…｡
ｱﾝﾀにしちゃ 筋肉質過ぎねえ｡
This is too buff to be you. Let me scrape some off around here.
この辺
そぎ落としたほうがいいな｡
Hey, what are you doing?! Give me a break! That's the only thing holding it up.
(長谷川)おぉい！ なにしてんの!!
勘弁してよ すんげえ微妙なﾊﾞﾗﾝｽで
立ってるから これ！
あぁ… そういうところも
似てるんだ ｱﾝﾀに｡
Is this bit true to life too?
I wonder if that part is like DORK's, too.
(神楽)ｱﾚも ﾏﾀﾞｵのと 似てるｱﾙか？
ｺﾗｧｱ！ ﾀﾞﾒ!!
そんなところ 指さしたら！
No! You're not supposed to point out that part!
おいおい ｳﾁの神楽ちゃんに➡
Hey, what dirty things are you showing to our Kagura-chan?!
なに 汚えもん
見せてくれてんの！
Just a minute!
(長谷川)待って！ これは
芸術的な意味でさ…➡
It's art! You see things like this in art textbooks all the time!
ほら 美術の教科書でも
あんじゃん！
Bastard! Are you trying to get Gin Tama canceled?!
ｸｿがぁあ！ 『銀魂』
打ち切らせるつもりかぁ!!
(長谷川)おぉい！ どこに
雪玉 ぶつけてんのぉお!!
Hey! Watch where you throw that snowball!
うぇいっ！
せいやっ!!
Take that!
Whoa! My Dandy Outstanding Refined Knob. In short, DORK!
(長谷川)うわぁああ！ ｵﾚの
ﾏｼﾞでﾀﾞﾝﾃﾞｨなおいなりさん➡
略して ﾏﾀﾞｵがぁ～っ!!
(２人)刺さったぁ～っ！
It's stuck!
Hey! How could you stick that dirty thing onto our masterpiece?!
(極悪興業)おんどりゃあぁ！
人の作品に➡
なに 汚えもん
刺してくれとんじゃい！
うわぁあ 来たぞ おい！
なんとかしろよ おいぃ!!
They're coming! Do something!
(長谷川)うわあぁあ～っ！
♪♪～
[Flight (crossed out)]
[Hey, Lady. Pant pant.]
[How you doing? Pant pant.]
[You're pretty. Pant pant.]
This is great work.
(お登勢)いい作品じゃないかい｡
(長谷川)あぁ そう…？
Oh, really?
Hey, you two were so callous! I bet you did that on purpose.
ちょっと！
２人とも ひどいっすよ!!
あれ わざとでしょ？
No, I didn't mean it.
わざとじゃねえよ だって あれ➡
But if we had left it as it was, I'm sure the PTA would've complained.
ほっといたら ＰＴＡから
苦情くるぜ｡
ｵﾒｴらが作ってるもんも
ｽﾚｽﾚなんだよ！
Yours is a hundred times worse.
おい！ ｵﾚ 今
すげえこと 思いついた！
Hey, I just came up with a great idea. Let's add some wings. Wings.
翼 付けよう 翼！
銀ちゃん すごいｱﾙ！
Gin-chan, that sounds great! How did you come up with such a great idea?
なんで そんな発想できるね!?
いやぁ なんか知らねえけど
ﾋﾟﾝときた ﾋﾟﾝと！
Well, I don't know, but it just came to me.
(桂)ん？ ｷｻﾏら 来ていたのか｡
桂さん｡
Oh? You guys are here, too?
Katsura-san...
むっ！ これは➡
Oh? This is the Neo Armstrong Cyclone Jet Armstrong Cannon.
ﾈｵｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ･ｻｲｸﾛﾝｼﾞｪｯﾄ･ｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ砲
ではないか！
完成度 高えな おい！
It has a very high-quality finish.
だから なんで知ってんだよ｡
And, how do you know?
Another name for it is "Running Thunder."
(桂)別名 ｢走る雷｣…
ﾊﾞﾙｶﾝ戦役における惨劇➡
It caused "The Seven Days of Fire" during the Balkans Campaign.
｢火の七日間｣を引き起こした
地獄の兵器だ…｡
さっきと 話 違うんですけど…｡
That's not the story I heard.
お前 なんで
こんなところに いるｱﾙ？
What are you doing here?
息抜きに ｵﾚも参加していてな…｡
I'm participating just for fun.
うわぁあ すごい！
ｱﾐｭｰｽﾞﾒﾝﾄ化してる!!
Wow! Great! It's like an amusement park!
こういうものは 子供たちを
楽しませるためにある｡
Something like this should be fun for children. I hope you guys like it.
お前たちも ぜひ
遊んでいってみてくれ｡
Hey, that's not the right way to play with it.
いや 遊び方 違うって｡
You mean this isn't for rock climbing?
(神楽)ﾛｯｸｸﾗｲﾐﾝｸﾞ的な…｡
No, this is a slide.
違う！ 滑り台だぞ それは！
それで 滑るな！
Don't slide with those on!
Hey, Zura, where're the stairs?
おい ｽﾞﾗ！ これ
階段 どこあんの？
(桂)ｷｻﾏら あくまでﾛｯｸｸﾗｲﾐﾝｸﾞ？
What are you guys, mountain goats?! And you were just on the stairs, fool!
明らかに 階段 途中まで
上がった形跡が あるだろうが！
(桂)あ～あ… 滑り台 傷だらけ…｡
Geez, the slide is all scratched up. I'll smooth it out.
すぐに磨くんだ…｡
(滑り落ちる音)
You bastards!
ｷｻﾏらぁあ！
さては ｸﾞﾗﾝﾌﾟﾘを狙うため
ｵﾚを 蹴落とす気か！
I know! You're trying to ruin my work so that you can win the grand prize!
そう簡単に いくか！
I won't let you win that easily!
(叫び声)
おい これ すごくね？
Hey, isn't it amazing?
You must be a genius. What made you think of attaching a slide to this?
お前 もしかして 天才じゃね？
普通 滑り台 つけようなんて
思いつく？
よく わかんないけど
ﾌｯと おりてきたね ｲﾝﾎﾟﾃｰｼｮﾝね｡
I don't know, but it just came to me. It was perspiration, uh-huh.
ｲﾝｽﾋﾟﾚｰｼｮﾝね…｡
You mean, inspiration.
Oh, hi, Gin-san. What a surprise to see you here.
(さっちゃん)あら…
銀さん 来てたの？ 奇遇ね｡
言っとくけど 私
知らなかったから｡
I swear I had no idea you were here. It's not like I was following you or anything. It's just...
別に 追いかけてきた
とかじゃなくて たまたま…｡
誰も 聞いてませんよ｡
あら？ これは➡
Nobody asked you...
Huh? This is a Neo Armstrong Cyclone Jet Armstrong Cannon. It's got a very high-quality finish.
ﾈｵｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ･ｻｲｸﾛﾝｼﾞｪｯﾄ･ｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ砲
じゃない！
完成度 高えな おい！
How do you even know that? You can't even see it's original shape anymore.
もう 原型 とどめてねえのに
なんで わかるんだよ！
(さっちゃん)惑星ﾂｪｻﾞｰﾝと
ｷｬｰｼｬｰﾝの星間戦争において➡
During the interstellar war between the planets Tuezzhan and Casshern,
ﾂｪｻﾞｰﾝ側を 勝利に導いた
ﾒｿｯﾄﾞ砲とは 裏腹に➡
this "Method Cannon" ultimately led the Tuezzhan to victory,
ずっと倉庫に
入れられっぱなしだった➡
and has been long since abandoned in a storehouse.
哀しき兵器よ｡
どうでもいいし 長えよ！
I don't care! That story's crap!
ひょっとして さっちゃんさんも
何か 作ってんですか？
Are you making a sculpture, too?
いや 別に… たいしたものは…｡
Well, it's nothing really...
Oh, really? I see something that has your name all over it.
なんか あそこに…
明らかに ｱﾝﾀが作ったとしか➡
思えない代物が
あるんですけど…｡
Don't get me wrong. Th-That's not Gin-san.
(さっちゃん)違うの！ あれは…➡
銀さんじゃないの… あの…
集英社 並びに 作者とは➡
Um... I'm not violating Shueisha's or any publisher's copyrights or anything.
一切 関係ない代物なの…｡
Its legs are far too long. Gin-chan's are shorter.
(神楽)なんか 異様に 足長いｱﾙ｡
銀ちゃん もっと短いよ｡
It's a glorification of him.
ちょっと 幻想
入っちゃってますね｡
Well, that's about right. Great. It looks exactly like me.
いや こんなもんだろ
すげえな おい！
そっくりじゃねえか！
これ ｸﾞﾗﾝﾌﾟﾘ いったんじゃね？
I bet this will win the grand prize. I can't possibly destroy it.
さすがに ｵﾚも
これは 壊せねえわ！
Eh? Really? Are you giving me a compliment?
えっ ｳｿ！ 褒めてくれるの!?
Well, I just said what I thought.
褒めるも なにも ｵﾚは
思ったことを言ったまでよ｡
この 不自然な手は
何なんですか？
Why are his arms positioned out like that?
Oh, that is...
(さっちゃん)あぁ… これは あれ｡
こうやって…➡
For this...and now it's complete.
これで完成… あぁ～っ！
あぁ～っ なにしてんの お前！
What are you doing? Gin-san's arms! Fix them quickly! Hurry!
銀さんの手が！
早く直して！ 早く!!
ごめんなさい！ あっ ﾒｶﾞﾈ…｡
S-Sorry! Oh, my glasses...
早く つけなきゃ｡
I'll put them right back on!
(お妙)なに…➡
What...
...are you doing, you dirty old geezer!
すんだ このどｽｹﾍﾞ野郎!!
なんで ｵﾚ～!?
Why me?!
あら 変…
なんだか 銀さんに➡
How strange. I thought you really were touching me, Gin-san. Sorry.
触られた気がしたから…｡
ごめんなさい｡
姉上 なんで ここに？
えぇ…➡
Sis, what are you doing here?
Well, the store I work at is entered in the competition.
私の店も 作品を出すのよ｡
…あら｡
Oh?
(お妙)これ ﾈｵｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ
ｻｲｸﾛﾝｼﾞｪｯﾄ･ｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ砲じゃない｡
This is a Neo Armstrong Cyclone Jet Armstrong Cannon.
完成度 高えな おい｡
違うから｡
It has a very high-quality finish, too.
No! It looks nothing like it did before!
明らかに違うよね これ｡
It looks so stupid. And there's nothing we can do with this Armstrong.
(お妙)ﾊﾞｶ面さげて
ﾎﾝﾄ しょうもない ｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞね｡
なに？ 結局 何なの ｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ砲！
What? What the heck is an Armstrong Cannon?!
それより せっかくだから
見ていって 新ちゃん｡
By the way, do you want to see our sculpture, Shin-chan?
私たちの作品 結構 凝ってるのよ｡
We worked really hard on it.
どう？ 結構 すごいでしょ｡
See? Isn't it great?
ねぇ 万事屋は
どんなものを作ったの？
What kind of work did the Odd Jobs do?
ん？ あの… あれだよ｡
Huh? Well... Um...
《は… 恥ずかしくて言えねえ｡
ｵﾚたち 今まで 何やってたの？
I'm too embarrassed to say. What did we do?!
ﾈｵｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ･ｻｲｸﾛﾝｼﾞｪｯﾄ
ｱｰﾑｽﾄﾛﾝｸﾞ砲って なぁに？
What is a Neo Armstrong Cyclone Jet Armstrong Cannon, anyway?
あんなの ただの
わいせつ物じゃねえか！》
That's just porn.
Ah. The truth at last.
あ 本音 言っちゃったよ ついに｡
《神楽:あれじゃあ
ｸﾞﾗﾝﾌﾟﾘどころか 参加賞も ﾑﾘｱﾙ》
There's no way we'd win the grand prize, or even a prize for participating.
《帰ろう… 恥をかく前に
こんなところ…》
Let's go home, before we publicly humiliate ourselves.
あら どこ行くの？
もうちょっと 私たちの雪像を…｡
Huh? Where are you going?
Don't you want to stay just a little longer to enjoy our snow statue?
(お妙の悲鳴)
(お妙)なにあれ！
雪像に 変なものが!!
What's that?! There's something weird on the snow statue!
ﾌﾊﾊﾊﾊ！ なにが ｸﾞﾗﾝﾌﾟﾘだ！
Who cares about the grand prize!!
そんなもんな 雪像 壊しちまえば
元も子もなくなっちまうんだよ！
If I can't have it, no one can!!
(長谷川)どうせ 雪なんて
時間が経てば 溶けちまうんだよ！
It's all gonna melt, anyway.
Into oblivion!!
すべて消えろ！ ﾌﾊﾊﾊﾊﾊ!!
(女性)ｷｬ～ｯ！ 変態よ 変態!!
There's the pervert!!
なにを ﾑﾀﾞなことを！
It's futile! Even if we made a new slide, they'd just destroy it again!
滑り台なんて作ったってなぁ
そんなもん 誰が滑るか！
(桂)滑り台なんて
なくなってしまえばいいんだ！
I don't want the slide anymore! I wish all the slides in the world would collapse!
(桂)世界じゅうの 滑り台は
全部 折れろ!!
(おりょう)あ～あ
あちこちで ｹﾝｶ｡ もう ﾑﾁｬｸﾁｬ｡
Oh, my! Everybody is fighting! What a mess!
お妙 どうする？ こりゃ
ｸﾞﾗﾝﾌﾟﾘ あきらめるしかないね｡
What should we do, Otae? We'd better give up on winning.
…お妙？
Otae?
(おりょう)ちょっと！
なにやってんの？
Hey, what are you doing?
Give me a break! No way will I give up! I'll win!
(お妙)ふざけんじゃないわよ！
絶対 ｸﾞﾗﾝﾌﾟﾘは取る！
ﾊﾞｰｹﾞﾝﾀﾞｯｼｭ 100個➡
We promised to share the 100 cups of Bäagen-Dash!
みんなで山分けって約束…
したじゃない!!
♪♪～
Bäagen-Dash? The winner gets 100 cups of ice cream?
ﾊﾞｰｹﾞﾝﾀﾞｯｼｭ？ ｸﾞﾗﾝﾌﾟﾘが ｱｲｽ100個？
おいおい おい… 冗談だろ｡
Hey, you've got to be kidding.
こっちは お前
金が たんまり出るっつうから➡
I worked so hard on a cold day because I thought we would get a cash prize.
寒いなか
あくせく働いてたっつうのに…｡
くさればばあ！
人のこと たぶらかしやがって～!!
Damn you, granny! You tricked me!
ﾅﾒんのも 大概にせえよ！
How dare you treat us like fools!
♪♪～
Otose-san, what's everybody doing? Is this a snowball fight competition?
お登勢さん… これって➡
みんな なにやってんでしたっけ？
雪合戦大会とかでしたっけ？
Nope...
んにゃ… 祭りだよ｡
It's a festival.
(花火の音)
(角屋の だんな)おい あれあれ！
あれ ｵﾚの作った花火！
You see that?! You see that?! I made those fireworks!!
It's a tiny bit lopsided...
(松)なんだか
いびつな形してるねぇ｡
(だんな)小せえこと
ｶﾞﾀｶﾞﾀ言うなや｡
Quit nitpicking!
《松:夏の夜空に舞い散る花火…｡
Fireworks sparkling in the summer sky...
ほんの一瞬 きれいな花を咲かせて
はかなく散っていく｡
Like a flower that blooms and disappears in an instant.
まるで 私ら 人のよう…》
But then... aren't we like that, too?
["Eating Ice Cream in Winter Is Awesome"]
Hey, hey, hey! What's this?!
なんだ こりゃ？
これ どう見てもｶﾀﾂﾑﾘじゃねえか｡
なに 嫌がらせ？
This looks like snails. Is this some kind of punishment?
これ あれですよ｡
ｴｽｶﾙｺﾞだか なんだかいう➡
This may be...escargot or whatever you call it. It's a delicacy...I think. And very expensive.
高級料理っすよ たぶん｡
(神楽)ﾏｼﾞでか？
Really?
ちょっと
ちょっと ちょっと これ！
Hey! That means this job's gonna be great!
今回の仕事は
期待できるんじゃないすか？
I mean, if they start feeding us all this fancy food...
いきなりの もてなしが
これだもん！
Idiot! Don't flip out too much.
ﾊﾞｶ野郎 舞い上がってんな｡
こんなもん食ったら 大恥かくぞ｡
They're testing us. To see if we're classy enough.
ｵﾚたちはな ﾏﾅｰを試されてんだよ｡
Look at the butler. He's smirking at us, isn't he?
見ろ お手伝いさん 半笑いだろ？
ﾎﾝﾄね｡
You're right.
What? But... what are we supposed to do with this snail thing?
でも そしたら この でんでん虫
何に使うｱﾙか？
皿だよ ｵﾒｴ｡
It's a plate! I think we put food on top like this then eat it.
これに 食い物 載せて
食うんだよ きっと｡
Plate... But it's already on the plate.
皿って…｡ 皿の上に
載ってんじゃないすか すでに｡
We put a coffee cup on the plate. It's like a saucer, right? It's classy.
ｺｰﾋｰｶｯﾌﾟだって
皿の上に載ってんだろうが｡
なんか そんなんがｵｼｬﾚなんだよ｡
You guys are real hicks. Watch how I use it.
(神楽)お前ら ﾎﾝﾄ 田舎もんな｡
私の 見とくね｡
すみませ～ん！ 水 おかわり！
Excuse me.
More water, please.
あ～ なるほど｡
お手伝いさん呼ぶときに使うんだ｡
I see. We use it to call the butler. That's why it's disk-shaped.
だから 円盤状なんだ｡
お手伝いさん ｵﾚ 箸 持ってきて｡
Can I have some chopsticks, please?
これ ちょっと
違うんじゃないですか？
I don't think that's right.
Yes, it is. Because he stopped smirking. Wait? Is he crying?
合ってるって｡
半笑い やめたじゃん｡
…あれ 泣いてる？
誰だ あれ｡ おい｡ ｶﾀﾂﾑﾘの妖精？
Who's that guy? What? Some mollusk demon?
He's got a snail on his head.
(神楽)頭の上に乗せてるよ
でんでん虫｡
Huh? Is that what we're supposed to do with it? Wear it?
ああいう感じなの？
ああいう感じで いいの？
Sorry I'm late, Mr. Odd Jobs. My mother is feeling ill and I...
(若だんな)
万事屋さん すみません 遅れて｡
ちょっと 母の体調が悪くて…｡
(若だんな)
なにやってんですか ｱﾝﾀら！
What are you guys doing?!
I'm sorry. We're not used to this kind of thing...
すみません… ﾎﾞｸら こういうの
あんまり慣れてないもので…｡
ﾊﾊﾊｯ… いや いいんですよ｡
それより さっそく➡
That's all right. By the way, I'm glad to see you're getting along so well with my father.
父と仲よくなったようで
安心しましたよ｡
Huh? Father?
えっ 父？
Yes. That's right, he's my father.
(若だんな)えぇ…
実は それ ﾎﾞｸの父でして…｡
(若だんな)
今回 あなたたちを呼んだのは➡
The reason I called you over here is to take care of him.
父の世話をしてもらおうと
思ってのことなんです｡
ﾃﾒｴ ｴｽｶﾙｺﾞじじい！
それは ｵﾚの…｡
You escargot old fart! Quit poaching my...
(だんな)誰が ﾋﾟﾀｺﾞﾗｽの定理じゃ！
Who's an egg, eh?!
だぁ～～っ!!
すみません｡
Sorry, my father hasn't been himself for some time now...
あの… ｳﾁの父
最近 ずっと こんなんでして…｡
(若だんな)一代で
角屋を ここまで大きくして➡
When he was younger, he was the greatest pyrotechnist in Edo. A master of fireworks!
江戸一番の花火師と
いわれた人だったんですが…｡
倒れた母の面倒をみるといって
引退して以来➡
But after he retired to take care of my mother,
who had become ill, something strange came over him.
様子が おかしくなって…｡
Junk Board Wandam. You're hairy today.
[Note: word play on Gundam robots]
(だんな)
よ～しよし ｼﾞｬﾝｸ･ﾎﾞｰﾄﾞ･ﾜﾝﾀﾞﾑ｡
今日も 毛だらけだな お前｡
[Note: Kuso means crap]
Hmm... He's Janno Kuso Gundam. It's a pretty name.
へぇ ｼﾞｬﾝﾉ･ｸｿｰ･ｶﾞﾝﾀﾞﾑっていうんだ｡
かわいいね｡
[Note: Mamire means covered, so JUMP covered in crap.]
No, no. JUMP Kuso Mamire.
(若だんな)夜中に徘徊したり
２～３日 戻ってこなかったり➡
He sometimes wanders around at night and leaves home for a couple of days.
Hmm...Kuso mamire. It's a pretty name.
手におえなくなってきまして…｡
He's getting to be a handful...
Right. It's Michael J. Dogs.
そうそう ﾏｲｹﾙ･Ｊ･ﾄﾞｯｸﾞｽってんだ｡
気が合うみたいですね｡
話は かみあってねえけどなぁ｡
They seem to be getting along well.
Kinda sad though. Old men... they get senile so quick, y'know?
にしても 男ってのは もろいねぇ｡
女は 旦那が死んでも➡
Old ladies do fine after their husbands die.
結構 元気にやってくもんなのよ
意外と｡
でも 男ときたら
嫁さんに先立たれると➡
But if a man's wife dies first, he usually just comes apart.
みるみる弱っていっちまうもんな
悲しいがな｡
But his wife isn't dead yet.
いや
まだ 奥さん 死んでませんよ｡
３年前に倒れてから
もうずっと寝たきりなんですって｡
She grew ill three years ago, so she's been bedridden.
He stopped making fireworks to take care of her,
その面倒みるって
花火やめたってのに➡
そのせいで
あんなになっちゃうなんて…｡
and, as a result, now he's behaving like that.
やっぱり 花火 好きだったんだ｡
I bet he loved fireworks.
Seeing him in this light, I feel really sorry for the old man.
そう思うと なんか
おじいちゃんも かわいそ… え？
ｸｿじじい！ なにやってんだ!!
Old fart! What are you doing?!
(だんな)ひゃっほ～い！
愛人に会いにいくんだって｡
He said he's going to meet his lover.
いるかぁ あんなもん!!
No way! He's already got one! Get him down before he escapes!
また 屋敷を抜け出すつもりかよ！
降りてこ～い!!
どけ！
Get out of the way!
There!
うわちゃあぁぁ～!!
うあぁぁ！
うぅぅ～｡
(水しぶきの音)
油断もｽｷもありゃしねえな｡
You've gotta be more careful.
ねぇねぇ
やりすぎじゃないですか？
Hey, wasn't that a bit much?
世話ですよ 世話｡
抹殺じゃないですよ 抹殺じゃ…｡
I thought we were supposed to take care of him... not kill him.
Ah! He hasn't given up yet!
あっ まだ あきらめてませんよ！
なに？
What?!
ｷｬｯﾎｯﾎｯﾎｳ～！
んだ？ この元気？
ﾎﾝﾄに老人か？
Why the heck is he so energetic? I thought this guy was old!
ｷﾞｬｯﾎｳｳｳｳ～！
♪♪～
ちょっと！
家 ﾒﾁｬｸﾁｬになってますよ！
Hey! You're destroying the house!!
てぇ～！
うわぁ！
(２人)わちゃぁぁぁ～!!
There!
♪♪～
Father, please stop this.
(若だんな)父さん
いいかげんにしてくれよ！
Mom is really sick! Can't you tell the good from the bad in these situations?!
母さんがこんなときに…｡
やっていいことと
悪いことがあるよ！
すみません…
ﾎﾞｸらも 悪ﾉﾘがすぎました｡
I'm sorry. We got carried away, too.
まあまあ 気にすんなよ｡
Don't worry about it. You fought well.
一生懸命やったよ お前ら！
お前が言うなよ ｸｿじじい！
Will you shut up, old fart!
From now on, Father, Mom is going to the hospital.
それから父さん… 母さん
入院することが決まったから｡
病状が悪化して もう家じゃ➡
She's gotten a lot worse.
We can't take care of her at home anymore.
どうにもならなくなってきたから｡
それじゃあ
おじいさんと おばあさん➡
Then he won't be with his wife at all.
離ればなれに…｡
(若だんな)父さん！
Father...
Don't you have anything to say?
なんか言いたいことないのかい！
I'm going out to see my lover.
愛人に会ってくる｡
なんてこった！
Good grief... I wonder if he even remembers mother at all.
母さんのことまで
忘れてしまったのか…！
ちょっくら 失礼します｡
Excuse me.
Please let him be.
(松)ほっといてあげて…｡
あの人を
あんなふうにしてしまったのは➡
I'm the one who made him this way.
私だから…｡
あの人から花火を奪ったのは
私だから➡
I took away his fireworks... So please...
もう… 自由にしてあげて…｡
Let him make his own choices.
(松)あの人は 十分
私に尽くしてくれた…｡
He's done enough for me.
大好きな花火の仕事を辞めて➡
He gave up the fireworks career he loved and worked very hard to take care of me.
一生懸命 私の世話をしてくれて｡
But I can't stand to see him miserable because he can't do what he loves anymore.
でも… やりたいことを我慢して➡
つらそうにしているあの人を
もう見たくないの｡
私のことは
忘れてくれてかまわないの｡
I don't mind if he forgets about me... His mind was filled with fireworks from the start anyways.
最初から あの人の頭の中は
花火でいっぱいで➡
私の入る余地なんて
なかったんだから…｡
There is no place for me in his life now.
そういうあの人に
私は 惚れたんだから…｡
And that's the man I fell in love with.
(若だんな)母さん…｡
ん？
Mom...
♪♪～
へぇ～ ここに愛人
かこってるわけか…｡
Hmm, so this is the place he hides his lover.
(お手伝いさん)そうですよ｡
That's right.
とびっきりの美女でございます｡
She's quite a special woman. We had better not interrupt them, Sakata-san.
邪魔するなんて下世話ですよ｡
坂田さん｡
Butler... So how do you come to be here?
お手伝いさん？ そういうｱﾝﾀも➡
こんなところにいるなんざ
ずいぶんと…｡
(爆発音)
おいおい… じいさん
ﾊｯｽﾙしすぎじゃねえの？
Hey, hey! Isn't the old man just a bit too energetic?
どういうﾌﾟﾚｰ？
(だんな)おえぇ！
What kind of position is he trying?
ｺﾞﾎｯ!!
Well, that was a failure!
失敗しちゃった～｡
There...
(だんな)よっこらしょっと！
花火か… やっぱりな…｡
Fireworks... Just as I thought...
ｱﾝﾀ いつから知ってたの？
お手伝いさん？
How long have you known about this, Butler?
もう ずっと前から…｡
Quite a long time...
外に出たきり
２～３日戻ってこねえときも➡
I heard that he left the house for a couple of days, but it was to come here, huh?
あるとか言ってたが 全部これか｡
たいしたもんだぜ｡
いろんなことを忘れても➡
What a man! He forgets most things, but not his fireworks.
花火だけは 忘れねえんだな｡
(お手伝いさん)
あの人の人生そのものですから➡
Fireworks are his life. They are part of his soul.
体に染みついてるんでしょう｡
記憶は朽ちても
往年の技は 消えない｡
Even as his mind deteriorates, his great skills do not.
奥様には悪いですが
旦那様は 一家庭人である前に➡
I feel sorry for his wife in saying this, but Master is an artisan.
職人であらせられる｡
And it's always made him less of a family man...
どうか このまま
そっとしてあげてほしい｡
Please...leave him alone. Let him die as an artist.
職人のまま
死なせてあげてほしい｡
You're saying that he's forgotten his wife, but the great skills he learned still burn strong?
女房を忘れても
体に染みついた技は➡
消えねえってか？
寂しい話じゃねえか｡
That's a sad story.
ｵﾚは 人間ってﾔﾂは➡
I think humans are better than that.
もっと ﾏｼな生き物だと
思うけどねぇ｡
頭の中の記憶がなくなろうが➡
Even if you lose your memory, you still retain it in your heart.
胸の真ん中に
ぶっささった記憶は➡
魂に刻んだ記憶は➡
You never lose the memories in your head, they are still deeply entrenched in your heart.
なにがあっても消えねえって➡
ｵﾚは そう思いたいね｡
That's what I believe.
(花火の音)
((だんな:おい！
見てるか？ 見てるか？
Hey! Did you see that? Did you?
Shut up! Of course I saw it!
(松)うっさいわねぇ 見てるわよ！
ったく！ なんで
このｸｿ寒い日に花火なのよ？
Why do I have to watch fireworks on such a cold day?!
(だんな)冬に花火ってのが
ｵﾂなんだろうが！
Fireworks in winter are special and so dazzling!
粋なんだろうが！
ﾌﾝ！
ちゃんと見とけよ！ お前！
Just watch this, all right?
…新作だかなんだか
知らないけど➡
I don't care about your new fireworks...
なんで試し打ちに 私が
付き合わなきゃいけないの？))
why do I have to come and watch your test fireworks?
(花火の音)
♪♪～
(松)｢嫁にこい｣って
やりたかったんだろうけどね➡
I'm sure he was trying to say "Come be my bride,"
字 間違って ｢塚にこい｣に
なってたのよ｡
but he misspelled a word and it said "Come be my mound."
(若だんな)ﾜｯﾊｯﾊｯﾊ…！
My goodness! Father hasn't changed a bit.
まったく 父さんときたら
今も昔も変わらんねぇ｡
まったくねぇ｡
寒くないかい？ 母さん｡
So true...
Aren't you cold, Mom?
大丈夫よ｡
I'm all right.
Right... that was 58 years ago today... I wonder if he still remembers...
《そう…
あれが58年前の今日のこと｡
あの人は 覚えているかねぇ？
Well, I don't suppose he could...
いや 覚えているわけないか》
((だんな:松
今日の日を記念して➡
Matsu! Every year this date, I'll light up the sky for you!
ｵﾚは 毎年 この日に
花火を打ち上げるぞ！))
《ﾌﾌ… ｳｿばっかり｡
Such a liar. That was the only time he ever did it.
私のために
花火を上げたのなんて➡
あれ１回だけだったわよ》
((だんな:松 お前は言ったな｡
Matsu, you said that people and fireworks
人間も花火も きれいな花を
咲かせるのは一瞬で➡
bloom like beautiful flowers for an instant and then fade away.
はかなく散っていくと…｡
たしかにそうかもしれない｡
That may be true.
でも 松… たとえ一瞬でもいい｡
But Matsu, even if it's only for a moment, I want you to bloom by my side.
お前は
ｵﾚの横で咲いていてほしい｡
散るときは
ｵﾚの横で散ってほしい｡
And when you fade away...do so at my side.
In return, I will...
かわりにｵﾚは お前の横に
何度でもきれいな花を咲かそう))
...make beautiful flowers bloom by your side again and again.
母さん！ 見てごらん
こんな季節に花火だよ！
Hey, Mom, look over there! Fireworks! At this time of the year!
これは きれいな…｡
冬に花火とは➡
It's so beautiful... Someone set off fireworks in winter.
粋な者もいたものですな｡
There's a person who knows the very best.
ﾎﾝﾄだねぇ｡
Yes indeed.
相変わらずいびつだけど…
きれいだねぇ｡
It's a tiny bit lopsided, but... it's so beautiful.
(花火の音)
わぁ！
(神楽)銀ちゃん 見て見て！
Gin-chan! Look! Look!
すごいすごい！
Wow!! So beautiful!
Are there any fireworks festivals scheduled today?
今日 花火大会なんて
ありましたっけ？
♪♪～
お～い 見てるか～？
Hey, are you watching?
[Preview]
My name is Katsura.
I'm a Ramen Hunter, who travels to all the ramen shops in Japan.
I've fallen in love with your ramen.
Please teach me how to make ramen under your tutelage.
The next episode: "Ramen Shops with Long Menus Never Do Well."
[Chased by the Shinsengumi, Katsura finds shelter in a ramen shop.]
[Ikumatsu, owner of "Daigo Ramen." Her husband was killed by Anti-foreigner Rebels.]